Ali Al-Ghatam, PMP®

Eastern Province, Saudi Arabia aligtm@gmail.com (+966) 50-390-7368 (+966) 54-407-4458

CAREER SUMMARY

I went to the Kyoto Sangyo University in Japan and majored in Information Communication Engineering. Afterwards, I started my career in the hospital of the ministry of health of Saudi Arabia as a Biomedical Engineer for 1.5 years. I worked for a leading EPC company as Project Engineer for 3 years providing proposal estimation, project control, cost engineering, and IT support for mega projects. I worked for different companies as IT Professional providing network/system administration, software development, and support to the IT infrastructure and operation for over than 6 years and as Project Manager for over than 3 years.

I am holding Project Management Professional (PMP)® credential and having Risk Management knowledge.

EXPERIENCE

Trainee of Machine Learning | Data Science | Data Engineering, Saudi Digital Academy and Coding Dojo, 2021-2022

- Joined Data Governance Bootcamp to learn the subjected topics
- Delivered daily assignments and weekly projects in these subjects
- Learned the following data governance subtopics:
 - Database and Data Analytics
 - R for Data Science
 - Python for Data Science
 - Machine Learning with R and Python
 - Data Management Body of Knowledge

Project Manager, Arabic Computer Systems Ltd., Khobar/Saudi Arabia, 2020-2021

- Assigned to manage the projects of Johns Hopkins Aramco Healthcare Centers (JHAH) in Saudi Arabia and Yanbu Aramco Sinopic Refinery (YASREF)
- Ensured the customer satisfaction by delivering equipment and services according to the Service Level Agreement (SLA)
- Handled PC Lease, Network Services, and SMP projects
- Manged delivery with the purchasing department
- Made sure equipment delivered to the local warehouse
- Planned resources and monitor the execution of the software imaging
- Got the PCs ready for the delivery to the customer site
- Planned and mange project resources
- Manged customer requests time by time

IT Project Manager, Imam Abdulrahman Bin Faisal University, Dammam/Saudi Arabia, 2017-2020

- Contracted by Al-Rumaih then by Nama Technology
- Handled Network Infrastructure Projects for the new facilities and buildings in the university
- Executed and monitored project plan and schedule
- Managed and led project team in formation and motivation towards commitment and completion of tasks
- Secured acceptance and approval of deliverables and milestones from sponsor and stakeholders
- Cultivated trust and communication with and amongst project's stakeholders

- Removed obstacles for project team
- Managed expectations by aligning projects to business goals, managing stakeholders and conflicts, and communicating project status, milestones, and unexpected difficulties/issues effectively
- Managed project issues, ensuring they are assigned and addressed appropriately, and escalate issues that cannot be resolved within project team
- Ensured quality standards are met
- Liaised with management and governance bodies, relevant to risks, complexity and impact of project

Freelancer, AliTech, Dammam/Saudi Arabia, 2013-Present

 Providing technical support for those companies requiring IT technical support, IT consultation, application support, project controlling, cost estimation, cost engineering, and project management services. Translation from/to Japanese/English/Arabic is also possible

IT Support Analyst, Emerson Process Management, Khobar/Saudi Arabia, 2011-2013

- Provided different aspects of support for the IT infrastructure and operation for all Emerson facilities in Saudi Arabia and Bahrain, including:
 - Monitoring helpdesk calls and provided second-line end user support
 - Performing Dell server maintenance and backups
 - Providing support for the specification, installation and maintenance of Dell PC hardware & software, together with telephone systems
 - Local and Wide area network monitoring
 - Local Area Network management and configuration
 - Providing support for internal applications as appropriate
 - Ensuring anti-virus and security patches are implemented in accordance with Emerson policies
 - Providing facilities management
 - Being aware of and reactive to any new products, developments and systems in the PC and server operations arenas that may be beneficial to the business
- Managed new IT requirements for the office expansion/renovation project

Project Engineer, JGC Gulf International Co. Ltd., Khobar/Saudi Arabia, 2008-2011 Assignment in Project Control Department, 2009-2011

- Performed a variety of cost engineering functions encompassing estimating, cost control, budget preparation, forecasting, and cost reporting under supervision
- Performed and ensured an effective cost control function for ongoing project
- Maintained current cost control database
- Supported project control manager on adhoc assignment
- Coordinated with the project members team to deliver the project deliverables on schedule
- Assisted PM in monitoring the project status by preparing project delivery progress report
- Prepared monthly project status report for the top management

Assignment in IT Department, 2008-2009

- Developed workflow procedures/systems
- Coordinated with Aramco network team to establish Aramco network connectivity
- Configured network and security appliances
- Participated in setup/planning of general IT policies
- Purchased HR system for the company

- Provided services and planning for the company operation as well as for the project executions
- Provided solutions for the engineering needs
- Supervised junior IT Engineers
- Acted as IT Lead Engineer for Aramco Tanajib Project

Technical Consultant, Temenos Middle East Ltd., 2007-2008

- Assisted senior consultants on integration of Temenos core banking system software with the local Saudi stock market (TADAWUL) as well as with the international stock market network (Reuters Network)
- Developed validation procedure using Java
- Performed testing for banking systems under supervision

System and Network Administrator, Jubail United Petrochemical Company through DAR Consulting Engineers, 2006-2007

- Participated in the network establishment project for the Plant Wide Information Management System
- Provided security monitoring, maintenance, and support for the Plant Wide Information Management System
- Provided systems/software upgrading, historical data backup, and data performance validation

Integration Specialist, Waseel ASP Ltd., 2005-2006

- Handled multiple Integration projects for different hospital information systems (HIS) with Waseel software for different medical services providers (hospitals/polyclinics)
- Participated in testing of Waseel software project
- Developed analysis application by Java to support the department daily work

Biomedical Engineer, Ministry of Health through United Medical Group and Scientific & Medical Equipment House contractors. 2004-2005

Assisted senior Biomedical Engineer on maintenance of the medical equipment

TRAINING

Data Governance

• Coding Dojo, 2021

Project Risk Management Professional Certification Exam Preparation (PMI-RMP®) Workshop

PMI-Arabian Gulf Chapter, 2009

Project Management Professional (PMP)®

• Project Management Institute, 2009



Introduction to jBase (A Banking System)

• Temenos Education Center, 2007

Course of training on CENTUM CS3000 R3 ENGINEERING (Related to the Control & Instrumentation DCS)

Yokogawa Middle East Training Center, 2006

Introduction to Oracle 10g: SQL

New Horizon Training Centers, 2006

aligtm@gmail.com (+966) 503907368

EDUCATION

Bachelor of Information Communication Engineering

Kyoto Sangyo University, Japan, 2004

Diploma of Japanese Language

International Institute for Japanese Language, Japan, 2000

SKILLS

Soft Skills

- Project and risk management, budget setting and cost control skills
- Analytical thinking and planning
- Strong verbal and written communication skills
- Accuracy an Attention to details
- Organization and prioritization skills
- Problem analysis, use of judgment and ability to solve problems efficiently
- Decision making, critical thinking, organizing, and planning
- Comparative Purchasing
- Presentation skills
- Leadership and Teamwork skills

Technical Skills

- Data analysis, data manipulation, data visualization
- Database modeling and design
- Database ER diagram design
- SQL query, DDL, Select, Conditional quires, SQL Operators, Aggregate Functions, SQL Joint and Sub-queries, SQL Views, SQL procedures, and SQL User-defined Functions
- NoSQL (MongoDB), Microsoft PowerBI, Tableau, Jupyter Notebook, and Python
- Java, JMF, J2ME, JSP
- PHP, HTML, JavaScript, MySQL, Apache
- Dealing with Oracle, MS SQL Server, and MySQL databases
- Crystal Reports
- Programming using C language
- Unix/Linux administration
- Dealing with IBM WebSphere Application Server (WAS) and messaging queue
- Using Eclipse as an IDE
- IBM Lotus Notes administration
- HP/Dell Servers initial setup and administration
- Using XML for integrating different systems
- Configuring Symantec Anti-Virus and Symantec Mail Security on the network
- Configuring Switches and Firewalls
- Configuring and administering Bluecoat (Proxy) appliance
- Corning cable system, fiber optic connection

OTHERS

Worked as Project Manager for organizing a workshop of around 15 attendees and 4 members team as volunteer social activity